字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
Asmik Ace Entertainment, Inc., Hakuhodo DY media partners, IMAGICA,
Sumitomo Corporation, Tokyu Recreation Co., Ltd.
And SHINCHOSHA Publishing Co. present
An Asmik Ace Entertainment, Inc. production
圆周率是3.141592653
(pi) equals 3.141592653
真痛苦，为什么不直接是三呢？
What a pain Why don't they just make it 3?
如果你把它变成三，就会得到一个正六边形，不是圆
If you made it 3, you'd get a hexagon, not a circle
嘿，阿根来了！
Hey, Root's here!
起立！
Rise
敬礼！
Bow
坐下！
Sit
接下来的一年，我会是你们的数学老师
I'll be your math teacher for the next year
你们已经知道了…我是阿根
You already know... I'm Root
你们看，今天我的发型不好看
As you see, I'm having a bad-hair day
今天，我希望你们了解一下我
Today, I want you to learn a little about me
这不是上课，所以你们不用记笔记
This isn't a lesson, so you don't have to take notes
他们叫我阿根
They've been calling me "Root,"
叫了十九年
for 19 years now
我得到了阿根这个名字，爱上了数学
The way I came by the name Root, fell in love with math,
直到今天站在了你们面前…
and ended up in front of you...
博士的爱情方程式
THE PROFESSOR AND HIS BELOVED EQUATION
我妈妈爱上了一个人，但不能跟他结婚
My mother loved someone she couldn't marry
她独自一人抚养我
and raised me on her own
没有受教育，而且无依无靠，我妈妈成为了一名管家
Uneducated and lonely, my mother became a housekeeper
因为对于她来说
because It was the only option available
那是唯一的选择
for a person of her talents
你的新客户可能有点难缠
Your new clients may be a bit of a handful
在过去的几年里，他们已经换了九个管家
They've gone through 9 housekeepers in the past few years
虽然我妈妈是家政中心最年轻的管家
Though the youngest housekeeper at the agency,
但是她已经有了十年工作经验
she already had 10 years experience
我英勇的妈妈
My spirited mother
以极大的自豪感追求着她的事业
pursued her profession with a fierce pride
打搅一下
Excuse me
我希望你照顾我弟弟
I would like you to look after my brother-in-law
弟弟…
Brother-in-law...
你丈夫的弟弟？
Your husband's brother?
没有人可以做很久
No one lasts long
每一次找了新人，我们都要从头开始
Every time we get someone new, we have to start all over again
真是麻烦
It's such a bother
这不是什么复杂的事情
I'm not asking for anything complicated
只是给他做吃的，照顾他
Just feed and look after him
从早上十一点到下午七点
from 11AM to 7PM
你弟弟在哪？
Where is your brother?
不要在堂屋和走廊之间走来走去
Don't come and go between the annex and the main house
你在我弟弟的房间工作
You work in my brother-in-law's house
他所有的事情
And it's up to you to solve
你要自己想办法解决
any problems with him yourself
你必须承诺这一点
You must promise me that
我会的
I will
要见一下你弟弟吗？
Shall I meet your brother?
没有必要
There's no need
即使他今天见了你，明天也不记得了
Even if he meets you today, he won't remember you tomorrow
什么意思？
What do you mean?
换句话说，坦白一点，他记忆出了问题
In other words, frankly, his memory is impeded
在一次交通事故中他大脑受到了撞击
He hit his head in a traffic accident
那次事故中我的腿瘸了
The same accident left me lame
我弟弟的记忆
My brother's memories
还停留在那天晚上
stop with the night we saw
我们一起在兴福寺的篝火旁看能舞的时候
a Noh play by bonfire at Kohfukuji Temple,
那是一九七五年的春天
in the Spring of 1975
事故已经过去了十年，但是在他看来
It's been 10 years since the accident, but in his mind,
我们昨天才刚刚看了能舞表演…
we've always just seen the Noh play yesterday...
换句话说，那些事情发生在昨晚
In other words, it always just happened last night
十年只有一天？
Ten years in a single day?
他甚至没有意识到我日渐衰老
He doesn't even realize that I age with each day's passing
十年前的我
The way I was 10 years ago,
是他现在脑海中的我…
is all he can see...
也是他以后脑海中的我
AlI he will ever see
不管什么事情，他的记忆都只持续八十分钟
In any event, his memory lasts 80 minutes
刚好是一小时二十分钟
That's exactly an hour and 20 minutes
周而复始
Over and over again
那么…
So...
周一早上十一点见？
I'll see you at 11am, Monday morning?
好
Yes
就这样，我妈妈成为了博士的管家
And so my mother came to work as a housekeeper in the professor's house
博士之所以能够学习数学
The professor had been able to pursue his study of mathematics
到英国的剑桥大学读书
all the way to Cambridge University in England,
得益于他哥哥在家族纺织品生意上的成功
thanks to his older brother's success in an inherited textile business
资助小弟弟完成了学业
which financed the much younger man's education
在获得博士学位之后
After he earned his Ph.D.,
他在一个数学研究所找到了工作
and found a position in mathematics research,
他哥哥去世了
his older brother passed away
哥哥的遗孀关闭了工厂
and his widow closed the factory,
在原来的地产上建起了公寓
built apartments on the property moved out to the country,
他们搬到农村，靠公寓收租生活
and lived on income from the apartments
但是，他们舒适的生活
But their comfortable lives
因为那场事故而改变了
were shattered by the accident
博士失去了工作
The professor lost his position,
靠嫂子养活
and became dependent on his sister-in-law's charity
你好！我是管家
Hello! I'm the housekeeper
你好！
Hello!
你好，我是新管家
Hello I'm your new housekeeper
你好
Hello
你的鞋子多少尺寸？
What's your shoe size?
二十四厘米
24 centimeters
哦，真是个尊贵的数字…
My, what a noble number...
是4的阶乘
It's the factorial of 4
什么是阶乘？
What is a factorial?
你将1到4的所有数字相乘
If you multiply all the whole numbers from 1 to 4,
得24
you get 24
你电话号码多少？
What's your telephone number?
五七六-一四五五
576-1455
你说5761455？
Did you say 5,761,455?
哦，太棒了
Why, that's wonderful
这跟十亿内的质数相等
That's equivalent to the prime numbers up to one billion
不管怎样，进来吧
In any event, come in
我工作很忙，没人管你
I'm busy working, so you're on your own
来吧，你自己管好自己
Go ahead and suit yourself
从那天开始
As of that day,
我妈妈跟博士重复每天早上的数学问侯
my mother and the professor repeated this mathematical greeting every morning
对于一个只有八十分钟记忆的博士
For the professor, whose memory spanned 80 minutes,
我妈妈永远都是新管家
my mother was always the new housekeeper
对于博士而言，培养数字
For the professor, bringing up math
在交流上是个悲剧
was a communication strategy
当他对说什么感到困惑的时候
When he was confused about what to say,
数字就会取代文字
numbers could always take the place of words
阶乘的“阶”
This character in the word "factorial"
指的是这些阶梯
is the character for staircase
“乘”是指相乘
The other character means multiply
所有数字
Whole numbers,
是指这些整数从1，2，3，4开始，无限延伸
refer to the integers which start 1, 2, 3, 4 and extend nfinitely
把这几个数相乘，得24
Multiply these and you get 24
那么24是4的阶乘
So 24 is the factorial of 4
现在，谁可以说出五的阶乘？
Now, who knows what the factorial of 5 is?
可以！124
Yes! 120
正确
Correct
七的阶乘呢？
How about the factorial of 7?
5，040
5,040
正确
Correct
你反应很快
You're fast
“素数”中的“素”
This character in "prime number"
是真实的意思
means genuine
天然而不加修饰
Like something genuine without embellishment
换句话说，只能被1或数字本身整除的数字
In other words, a number which is on y divisible by 1 or itself
例如…
For instance...
2，3，5，7
2, 3, 5, 7,
11，13，17
11, 13, 17,
19，23，29…
19, 23, 29...
这些素数
These prime numbers
就像天空中无穷尽的星星
are as infinite as the stars in the night sky
不受任何已知法则的支配
No known rules govern them
我在这里，完全自立
I am here, utterly self-sustaining
换句话说，就像你们每一个都是独一无二的
In other words, just like all of you, each one is unique
绝对高贵不屈
Utterly noble and unbending,
这些数字保持孤高
these numbers remain aloof
“孤高”
"Aloof"
博士在世界上最珍视的
What the professor cherished most in this world,
是这些素数
were these prime numbers
他真的爱数字吗？
Did he really ove numbers?
当然，他爱的对象可能有点怪，但爱情本身不奇怪
Sure, the object of his affect ons may have been eccentric, but not his love
他珍视它们，陪伴它们，不求回报
He cherished them, served them without compensation,
永远，尊重它们
respected them, always
不离不弃，一刻也不抛下它们
never straying from them for even a moment
很抱歉打搅您
I'm sorry to bother you
您中饭想吃什么？
What would you like for lunch?
有什么喜欢的，或者不喜欢的吗？
Any preferences, dislikes or allergies?
告诉我好一些
It would help to know
您有什么意见？
What do you think?
我会去准备一些吃的，您有什么意见？
I can go ahead and just fix something, but what do you think?
欢迎说出您的想法
I'd welcome your opinion
我没什么说的
I have nothing to say
现在，我在思考
I'm thinking, now
你闯了进来，打搅了我去爱我的数字
You come barging in and interrupt my love for my numbers
就像偷窥人家上厕所一样粗鲁
It's as rude as peeping into a toilet
非常抱歉，请原谅
I'm terribly sorry Excuse me
我的记忆只能持续八十分钟
My memory lasts only 80 minutes
新管家
The new housekeeper
您可以多吃点吗？我做了很多
Would you care for more? I made plenty
四月七日
April 7th
日子一天天过去
Every day adds to the others
我们应该心怀感激，春天终于来了
We should be grateful spring has finally come
你好！
Hello!
你好
Hello
我是你的新管家
I'm your new housekeeper
你的鞋子多少尺寸？
What's your shoe size?
二十四
24,
四的阶乘
the factorial of 4
真好
That's wonderful
多么尊贵的数字…
What a noble number...
打搅一下
Excuse me
在
Yes
请帮我把这个寄到
Please send this to The Journal of Mathematics,
这个地址
at this address
好，没有问题
Sure, no problem
寄平信吗？
By regular mail?
对
Yes
一百七十元
That'I be 170 yen
谢谢你
Thank you
我回来了
I'm home
欢迎你回来，谢谢你帮忙
Welcome home, thanks for your work
不用谢
Not at all
你经常把论文投递给杂志吗？
Do you often submit your papers to magazines?
对…
Right...
我把我的证明寄给了《数学杂志》三十七期，今天…
I sent my proof to The Journal of Mathematics, Vol. 37 today...
很好
That's good
哦，不！
Oh, no!
我应该寄快件，只有第一个寄到的才可以拿现金奖
I should've sent it express Only First Place takes a cash prize
不，没有必要寄快件
No, there's no need to send it express
比其他人更早给出证明，这很重要
It's important to arrive at the truth before anyone else,
但更重要的是这个证明要漂亮
but it's more important that the proof be beautiful
证明还有漂亮和丑陋？
There are such things as beautiful or ugly proofs?
当然有
Of course
在一个真正正确的证明里
In a truly correct proof,
无懈可击而引人注目的推理
air-tight and compelling reasoning coexists without contradiction,
与柔顺的逻辑共存，毫无冲突
with supple logic
就像没有人可以证明为什么星星很漂亮
Just as no one can prove why stars are beautiful,
要表达数学的美，很难
it's difficult to express the beauty of mathematics
你什么时候生日？
What's your birthday?
二月二十日
February 20th
多么迷人的数字
What a charming number
看一下这个
Take a look at this
在大学的时候
Back in college,
我关于超越数的论文获得了校长奖
I won the President's award for my paper on Transcendental Number theory
了不起的荣誉！
What a great honor
不，这没关系
No, that doesn't matter
你可以读出这个数字吗？
Can you read the number?
“学长奖，284号”
"President's Award No. 284"
意思是你是第284个获得这个奖的人？
Does that mean you're the 284th person to receive the honor?
我想是的
I suppose
问题是284和220
The question is 284 and 220
没时间洗碗了，跟我走
This is no time to be washing dishes Come with me
你有什么想法？
What do you think?
这个，我…
Well, I...
都有三个阿拉伯数字…
Both have 3 digits...
我可以怎么表达呢？
How can I phrase this?
在超市的肉类柜台上
At the meat counter at the supermarket,
如果有两袋绞碎的牛肉，一袋220克，另一袋284克
if there are two packets of ground beef, one 220 grams the other 284,
对我看来就是一样的
they seem the same to me
扫一眼，看上去相似
One quick glance and they look similar
它们都在200那一排，而且所有数字都是偶数
They're both in the 200 range and all the numbers are even
目光敏锐
That's a keen insight
直觉很重要
Intuition is important
从你的内心，直观地抓住数字
Grasp the numbers intuitively, from your heart
你知道约数吗？
You know what a divisor is?
对，我想我还记得以前学过…
Yes, I think so I remember studying them...
我们把220和284的约数都写出来
Let's write out all the divisors for 220 and 284,
除了它们自身
excepting themse ves
1，2，4，5，10
1, 2, 4, 5, 10
11，20，22
11, 20, 22,
44，55，110
44, 55, 110,
1，2，4
1, 2, 4,
71，142
71, 142
你可以在心里面算出所有的约数？
You can calculate all those divisors in your head?
我只是用到你刚才所用的直觉
I'm just using the same intuition you did
进入下一步
Onto the next step
加起来
Add it up
慢慢来
Take your t me
做好了
I'm done
正确
Correct
你会这样看吗？
Will you behold,
这个漂亮的数字链
this beautiful chain of numbers
将所有284的约数加起来，得220
Add all the divisors for 284 and you get 220
将所有220的约数加起来，得284
Add all the divisors for 220 and you get 284
它们是亲和数
They're amicable numbers
亲和数？
Amicable numbers?
亲和数
Amicable Numbers
这种配对很稀少
Such pairs are very rare
即使是费马和笛卡尔，也只是每人发现了一对
Even Fermat and Descartes only discovered one pair each
它们是上帝的设计，要彼此相亲相爱
They're numbers bound to each other by God's design
上帝的设计…
God's design...
美吗？
Isn't it beautiful?
你的生日，跟我手表上刻的数字
Your birthday and the number engraved on my wristwatch
完美地纠缠在一起
are so perfectly intertwined
第一个发现亲和数的是毕达哥拉斯
The first person to discover amicable numbers was Pythagoras
毕达哥拉斯作出了他的著名论断
Pythagoras made his famous statement,
“万物皆数”
"Number is the within of all things"
在公元前六世纪
In the 6th century, B.C.
数字存在的历史有这么久吗？
Have numbers been around that long?
当然，数字的存在历史比人类久远
Of course Numbers existed before humans,
不，甚至，久远很多，很多
no, even much, much longer
甚至早在世界存在之前，它们就已经存在
They existed even before this world was born
但是人类创造了数字，是吗？
But humans invented numbers, right?
绝对不是，没有任何人目睹了数字的诞生
Not at all. No human being witnessed the birth of numbers
它们一直在那，从始至终
They have always just been there, all along
人类所能做的
All humans can do is express with words,
就是用文字表达出数字告诉我们的一切
what numbers provide for us
你们有什么看法？
What do you think?
关注发现更多的亲和数？
Care to discover some more amicable numbers?
顺便提一下，接下来最小的一对亲和数是
By the way, the next smallest amicable numbers are
和1210
1184 and
四个阿拉伯数字！
Four digits!
不可能！
No way!
这一对…
This pair...
在一八六六年…
In 1866...
意大利人，帕格尼尼
Paganini, an Italian,
尼科洛・帕格尼尼，发现了这一对
Nicolo Paganini, discovered this pair
你相信吗，那时候，帕格尼尼只有十六岁
Can you believe it, at the time, Paganni was 16 years old
在读高中！
In high school!
重要的是努力思考，不要放弃
What matters is to think it through without giving up
你不是“巨人迷”，我很高兴
I'm so glad you're not a Giants fan
是“老虎迷”
Always been a Tigers fan
我和我儿子也是大“老虎迷”
My son and I are huge Tigers fans, too
你有个儿子？
You have a son?
对
Yes
他有多大了？
How old is he?
十岁
Ten years old
十？
Ten?
为什么，他只是个孩子
Why, he's just a boy
你儿子现在在哪，做什么？
And where is your son now, what's he doing?
哦，我不确定
Oh, I'm not sure
可能在跟朋友们一起玩
Probably playing ball with his friends
“哦，我不确定”
"Oh, I'm not sure"
你应该多关心他
You should be more concerned
马上就要天黑了
It's going to get dark, soon
不要担心，他有每天的固定安排
Don't worry, he has a daily routine
固定安排？
Routine?
你每天都抛弃你的儿子
You routinely abandon your son
来这里做碎肉饼？
to make hamburgers here?
我不是抛弃他
I don't abandon him
只是，这是我的工作…
It's just that this is my job...
你不在的时候谁照顾他？
Who looks after him while you're away?
你丈夫很早回家？
Your husband comes home early?
哦…
Oh...
我明白了
I get it
他有个奶奶
He has a grandmother
不，不幸的是
No, unfortunately,
他没有爸爸，也没有奶奶
he has no father or grandmother
就只有我跟儿子两个人
My son and I live alone together
你儿子一个人在等你？
Does your son wait for you alone?
在饿着肚子等你？
He waits for you with an empty stomach?
这时候他妈妈在给一个陌生人做晚饭…
While his mother cooks supper for a stranger...
我的晚饭…
My supper...
这很糟糕
This is awful
不可以这样，不可以
This can't be, it can't
你不需要担心
You don't need to worry
一直以来就只有我们两个
It's always been just the two of us
他现在十岁了，一个人没事的
He's 10 now, he's fine on his own
他知道这里的电话号码
He knows the phone number here
我们的房东也可以帮忙
Our landlord can always help
不不不，你不可以让孩子一个人
No, no, no You can't leave a child alone
如果炉灶掉下来起火了怎么办？
What if the stove falls over and there's a fire?
如果糖果卡住了喉咙，谁来救他？
Who will save him if a candy gets stuck in throat?
想想就觉得可怕
It's terrifying to consider
我受不了，你现在必须回家
I can't bear it You must go home, now
就是现在，回家
Right now, go home
不会很久的，我要做好碎肉夹饼
I won't be much longer I just have to cook the burgers
不要管这个
Forget about that
如果做夹饼的时候，你儿子被火烧死了怎么办？
What if your son dies in a fire while you're cooking the burgers!
让我…
Just let me...
现在，听着
Now, listen
从明天开始，你把你儿子带过来
Starting tomorrow, just bring your son with you
让他放学后来这里
Just have him come here, right after school
你在这做饭，我们三个一起吃
You'll cook supper here and the three of us will eat together
但是，这…
But that's...
一个成年人怎么可以
How dare a grown man
当着一个饥饿的小孩的面只顾自己填饱肚子？
stuff his face in front a hungry child
但是我的合同…
But my contract...
但是，如果你不在这给他做饭，等你回去的时候
But if you don't cook him supper, until you get home from work,
你儿子八点才能吃到东西
your son can't eat until after 8PM
那样不对
That's not right
不要看轻我，不要
Don't underestimate me, assuming
我明天会忘记
I'll have forgotten by tomorrow
我什么都会忘记
I'll have none of that I won't forget
她的儿子
Her son
十岁
10 years old
如果你背弃承诺，我不会原谅你
If you break our promise, I won't forgive you
你好！
Hello!
你从很远的地方过来，好孩子，好孩子
You've come a long way Good boy, good boy
谢谢你，谢谢你
Thank you, thank you
我看得出来你有个聪明脑袋
I can tell you've got a wise heart in there
好了，你是阿根
All right, you're a Root
你接受任何数字，一个也不拒绝
You accept any number that comes your way, rejecting none
是真正慷慨的符号，阿根
A truly generous symbol, Root
过来
Come on in
从那天开始，我被叫做阿根
Ever since that day, I've been called Root
我的头…
My head...
像这个根号一样平
was as flat as this root symbol
我记得很清楚，博士跟我一起探寻
I remember well, the day the professor and I tried to find out,
会发生什么奇迹
what kind of magic happens,
你将数字放在根号里面
when you put numbers inside this root symbol
1的平方根
The square root of 1
1的根…
The root of 1...
有“+1”和“-1”，两个
There's +1 and -1, two of them
“-1”的平方根
The square root of -1
“-1”的平方根…
The square root of -1...
是“+1”还是“-1”？
Is this +1 or -1?
不可能
Impossible
为什么？
Why?
因为“+1”和“-1”的平方根
Because the square roots of +1 and -1,
都是“+1”
are both +1
很对
Exactly
好，那么“-1”的平方根
AlI right, so the square root of -1,
究竟是什么？
what exactly is it?
没有这样的数字
There is no such number
不，它就在这里
No, it's right here
为了回答这个问题
To answer this,
意大利数学家，拉斐罗・邦别利…
the Italian mathematician, Rafael Bombelli...
拉斐罗・邦别利
Rafael Bombelli,
发明了一个新数字，“i”
invented a new number, "i"
那是在十六世纪，“i”
This was in the 16th century, "i"
“i”是一个虚数
"i" s an imaginary number
因为它是一个很谦虚的数字…
Because it's a very modest number...
所以用了“谦虚”的“虚”字
It's written with the character for "candor,"
而且…
and...
谦卑的性格
the character for humility
从来没有出现在可见的世界
It never appears in the visible world,
但总是存在于我们心里
but it's always inside our hearts,
用它短小的臂膀
using its short little arms
支撑起它的整个世界
to support its whole world
从“i”你可以想到什么？
What do you magine from this "i"?
想象一下看
Just try to imagine
“Iloveyou！”我爱你里面的“I”
The "I" in "I love you!"
对，那个“I”
That's right, that "I"
但是那个“I”
But that "I" naturally
通向“爱”
leads to "love"
打搅一下…我可以做什么吗？
Excuse me... May I help you?
我喜欢看着你做饭
I like watching you cook
为什么你一定要…
Why do you have to...
不停地翻动肉片呢？
keep moving the meat around?
因为锅子中间到边缘的温度不一样
The temperature varies from the center to the sides of the pan
为了让菜受热均匀，要变动它们的位置
To cook things evenly, you have to shift them around
我明白了
I see
它们分享每一个点
They all share every spot, so that one can't
那么就没有谁一直霸占最好的点
monopolize the best spot
什么事情…这么迷人？
What is... so fascinating?
我只是在做饭
I'm just cooking
哦，如此平和
Oh, it's so peaceful
阿根很快就回来了
Root will be back, soon
阿根？
Root?
他是我十岁的儿子
He's my 10 year old son
他有个方脑袋，所以叫阿根
He has a flat head, so he's Root
哦，我明白了，你有个儿子
Oh, I see, you have a son?
对
Yes
我回来了！
I'm home!
看，阿根来了
See, here's Root
有什么比听到孩子喊“我回来了”更暖人心房呢？
What's more heartwarming than a child calling, "I'm home"
真是个好孩子
That's a good boy
我看得出来你有个聪明脑袋
I can tell you've got a wise heart in there
洗手，然后我们吃饭
Wash your hands and let's eat
你能吃多少就吃多少，小孩的任务就是长大
You've got to eat all you can A child's job is to grow
不能因为不爱吃就不吃
And don't eave anything just because you don't like it
如果你还饿
And if you're still hungry,
就帮我吃一些
just help yourself to some of m ne
好，谢谢！
Sure, thanks!
每一次我看到孩子们开心地玩耍
Every time I see children happily playing,
一首诗就浮现在我的脑海
an old poem comes to mind
“看别人的小孩嬉戏”
"To see others' children frolic
“泪水止不住，为了我那失去的孩儿”
"brings ceaseless tears for my own, now lost"
我的心…
My heart is....
是e
(pi).i th power of e =-1
就像这个方程式永远等于-1
Just as this equation will forever yield -1,
我们的新生活永远都丢失了
the new life we made is now lost forever
对于我们，开始步出生命的轨迹
To us, having stepped off course,
没有人施以援手
none will offer a friendly hand
来分担你的不幸
To share in your misfortune
这是我唯一的愿望
That is my only wish
致我心爱的N
To my beloved N
可以帮我个忙吗？
Can I ask you a favor?
我能帮一定帮
If I can be of help, sure
考考我吧
Try me out
你会修收音机吗？
Can you fix the radio?
修收音机？
Fix the radio?
对
Yeah
我来这里就没法关注棒球比赛了
When I come here, I can't follow the baseball games
这里没电视机，收音机又坏了
There's no TV, the radio's busted
职业棒球队里…
Oh... professional baseball
你支持哪个队？
Which team are you for?
你没看到我的帽子吗？老虎队
Can't you see from my cap? The Tigers
对，老虎队
Oh, right, the Tigers
我是江夏的球迷
I'm an Enatsu fan
江夏是老虎队的王牌投手
The Tiger's ace pitcher, Enatsu
是啊！太好了
Really! Oh, great
那你一定要修好收音机了
Then you have to fix the radio
现在江夏的投手责任得分率是多少？
What's Enatsu's Earned Run Average now?
他有几个三振出局？
How about his Strikeouts?
他们把江夏卖掉了
They traded Enatsu away
还有，他已经退役了
Besides, he's already retired
退役了？
Ret red?
晚安
Good night
老虎队今晚有比赛吗？
Are the Tigers playing tonight?
希望他们能赢
I hope they're winning
我应该闭嘴的
I should've kept my mouth shut
我不知道博士是江夏迷
I had no idea the professor was such an Enatsu fan
不管怎样，我们不希望他难过
No matter the reason, we don't want him to suffer
当然了
Of course not
博士不断重复自己的话
The professor repeats himself constantly
我们说好了
Let's promise
我们永远不要说“你已经告诉过我了”
We'll never say, "You already told me that"
好的，我一定不说
Sure, I promise
别担心，明天他又会恢复原状了
Don't worry, tomorrow he'll be back the way he was
在博士记忆里，江夏永远是老虎队的王牌
In the professor's mind, Enatsu will be the Tiger's ace all over again
今天天气真好
It's such a glorious day out
你愿意去公园散步吗？
Would you like to take a stroll in the park?
有什么好处呢？
What would be the point?
散步促进血液循环
Walking improves your circulation,
这样你就会有更好的数学灵感了
so you might get some good math ideas
腿部和大脑…
Blood circulates differently
血液循环是不同的
to the legs and the brain
我跟你在一起
Now listen, I'm with you here
你不会一个人回家吧
Don't you just go home alone
当然不会，别担心
Sure, don't worry
种田和研究数学很相近
Farming is the work most similar to mathematics
种田？
Farming?
没错
That's right
你选择种子，耕耘土地
You select and plough the land,
种下并培育种子
plant and grow your seeds
数学家选择他们的研究领域
Mathematicians choose their field,
种下他们的种子并努力培育它们
plant their seeds and work hard cultivating them
种子就会长大了
The seeds themselves do all the growing
什么都可以吃
Anything's edible
看见了吗？
Do you see?
蔬菜并不只在商店能买到
Vegetables aren't just things you buy in a store
为什么，那是野草
Why, that's a weed
这是土壤的气味，很好闻
It's scent of the earth, good smell
用芥末酱拌着吃会长力气
Toss it with some mustard sauce for strength
回去的时候到了，阿根要回家了
I say it's time to head back Time for Root to come home
阿根？
Root?
阿根是我的儿子
Root is my son
你有个儿子？
You have a son?
是的！
Yes!
那我们赶快回家，没时间摘野草了
Let's hurry home then, hardly the time for picking weeds
听着，每个难题都有其韵律
Listen, now Every problem has its rhythm
如果你把难题大声读出来，并且抓住它的韵律
If you say the problem out loud and grasp its rhythm,
你就能完全沉浸其中
you can contemplate it in its entirety
你就会开始猜测哪些地方暗藏陷阱
and you'll begin to surmise the suspicious areas where traps lurk
买两块手帕和两双袜子，需三百八十元
"I bought 2 handkerchiefs and 2 pairs of socks for 380 yen
买同样的两块手帕和五双袜子
"The same 2 handkerchiefs and 5 pairs of socks,
需七百一十元
"cost 710 yen"
“求每件商品的价格”
"How much did each item cost?"
没错，这题可能是…
It's true, this may be
你今天碰到最难的问题
your toughest problem today
不过你读得这么好听
But you read it out loud so beautifully
手帕，袜子，价格
Handkerchiefs, socks, cost
你完全掌握了韵律
You had the rhythm down perfectly
枯燥的作业…
A boring assignment,
读起来像一首诗
read like a complete verse
好，让我们把题画出来
All right, let's try making a drawing of it
过来
Come over here
准备好了吗？
Ready?
先画两块手帕
First the 2 handkerchiefs
再画两双袜子
Then the 2 pairs of socks
这不像袜子，像是肥毛虫
Those don't look like socks, they look like fat caterpillars
我画给你看
I'I draw them for you
每次…
In every situation,
博士都不会直接给出正确答案
the professor wasn't just after the right answer
博士宁可…
The professor preferred...
费尽心机想办法打破我因为答不出来…
the bizarre mistakes born of trying too hard, to my falling silent,
而保持的沉默
for lack of an answer
不管我显得有多愚蠢
No matter what stupid dead end I wound up in,
博士总是能替我找到积极面，并为我骄傲
the professor always found something positive for me to be proud of
你做对了，对！
You're right, right!
教我棒球好吗？
Teach me baseball, OK?
棒球…
Baseball...
你中学时打过棒球，对吗？
You played baseball in high school, right?
是的，我热爱棒球
Yes, I loved baseball
我读大一的时候，打进过我们那里的半决赛
In our junior year, we lost the Prefecturals in the semi-finals
请你指导我们练习好吗？
Will you coach our practices? Please
好吧
Sure, all right
All right
棒球…
Baseball...
练习
Practice
对不起…
Excuse me...
我能告诉你我的发现吗？
May I tell you what I discovered?
把28的约数加起来…
If you add up 28's divisors,
就等于28
you get 28
嗯…
Hmm...
这是完全数
That's a perfect number
完全数…
A perfect number...
最小的完全数…
The smallest perfect number...
是6
is 6
对啊，这没什么大不了的
You're right, it's no big deal
不，这很了不起
Oh, yes it is
他们是表达完美内含的珍贵数字
They're precious numbers which embody the meaning of perfection
笛卡尔说过
Descartes said,
就像完美的人是罕有的一样
"just as perfect humans are rare,
完全数也是很罕有的
"so are perfect numbers"
几千年来…
Over the past several thousand years,
只发现了三十个完全数
barely 30 have been found
只有三十个？
Only 30 of them?
对，完全数28
Yes, the perfect number 28
也是江夏的号码，老虎队的王牌投手
is also Enatsu's number, the Tiger's ace pitcher
在我脑海中
Inside my head,
我能回忆起他比赛的每个细节
I can recall every detail of his games,
从一九六七年他凭借十个三振出局…
from his first professional win with the Carps in 1967,
第一次赢得佳能杯，到一九七三年八月三十日…
with 10 Strikeouts, to a game on August 30th, 1973,
那天他在加时赛里…
when he hit that game-ending home run
打出了终赛全垒打
in a no-hit, no-run, extra-innings game
我给你们看完全数的另一个特点
Let me show you one more feature of perfect numbers
完全数…
Perfect numbers,
可以表示成相邻数的加总
can be expressed as a sum of consecutive whole numbers
1 + 2 + …，
Here goes 1 plus 2 plus
3 + 4 + …，
3 plus 4 plus
5 + 6 +…，
5 plus 6 plus
哇，二十八
Wow, 28
对，二十八
Right! 28
瞧，二十八
See, 28
直到今天，完全数还是个谜
To this day, perfect numbers are shrouded in mystery
还没有人证明出…
No one has ever proven
一共存在着多少完全数
that an infinite number of perfect numbers exists
老师，他也教你棒球了吗？
Teacher, did he also teach you baseball?
是的
Of course
博士在大学读数学系的时候…
The professor had tried to pursue baseball
他还在打棒球，不过他的肩膀受了伤
as a college math major, but he injured his shoulder
他就放弃了
He gave it up
他的肩膀受了伤…
He injured his shoulder,
但他年轻时候的经验和技巧
but his experience and the practice
是实实在在的
he'd put in as a young man were the real thing
游击手
Shortstop
二垒
Second base
对了
That's right
对，打得好
Right, here goes
越快越好
As fast as you can
打出了圆滚线
That's the Cycloid Curve
对
Right
博士怀着巨大的热情…
The professor repeated the basics over and over again,
一遍一遍地教我们基础训练
teaching us baseball with a great deal of love
我和我的队友商量好…
My teammates and I promised that no matter how many times
不管他教了我们几遍同样的东西，我们都不说“你已经教过了”
he taught us the same thing, we'd never say, ''You already taught us that"
致我永远的爱人N…
"To my eternally beloved N...
“你永远不会忘记的人上”
"From the one you must never forget"
这是个高飞球，快击中它
That's a high fly, call the bal
你没有击中，起来吧！
You didn't call the ball Get up!
你没事吧？别动
Are you OK? Don't move
救护车！
An ambulance!
救护车？他不动就没事了
Ambulance? He'll be fine if he doesn't move
快叫救护车
Call an ambulance now
如果我不打出那个高飞球
If I hadn't hit that fly ball
都是我的错
It's my fault
这是常有的事
It happens all the time
给
Here
在纸上画一条直线
Try drawing a straight line here
这会让你平静下来
lt'll calm you down
来吧
Go ahead
对，这是一条直线
That's right, that's a line
但你想想看
But think about it
你画的这条直线有头有尾
The line you drew has a beginning and an end
这就意味着…
Which means,
你画的线是一段…
you've drawn a line segment linking the shortest distance
两点间的距离
between two points
直线的定义是没有尽头的
The definition of a line doesn't include ends
应该是没有界限的
It's supposed to continue indefinitely
但一张纸是有边界的
But there are limits to a piece of paper
因为能力有限…
as there are to your strength
我们只能…
So we agree to calI what's
把线段称为直线
really a line segment, a line
真正的直线在哪？
Where can a true line be found?
只有…
Only...
在这里
in here
永恒的事实是看不见的，是不会因为…
The eternal truth is invisible and unswayed by matter,
事件，自然现象或是情绪而动摇的
natural phenomenon or emotions
那个看不见的世界…
The invisible world
支撑着看得见的世界
supports the visible world
最重要的东西我们在心中才能找到
The important things, we have to see with our hearts
你不必担心
You don't have to worry
根的含义是坚强
The root symbol is sturdy
它保护每个数字
It protects every number
你好吗？
Hey! How are you?
真不负责任
How irresponsible
你怎么能把他留给博士管！
How could you leave him in the professor's care!
他真的没事？
Is he really all right?
是的，他对他处理得当
Yes, he treated him appropriately
他没做错什么？
He did nothing wrong?
无懈可击…
A little more than necessary...
瞧
Look
第一颗亮起来的星星
There's the first star, up there
对不起，我在医院说错了话
I'm sorry. What I said at the hospital was wrong
我…
I won't...
永远忘不了博士悲伤的脸…
ever forget the professor's sad face...
永远
Ever
我一度不相信博士…
That I doubted the professor, even for a moment,
我很惭愧
is something I'm ashamed of
我道歉
I apologize
好吧，我接受了
OK, I accept
我们拉钩
Let's make-up
他说他会来看我们下次的比赛
He said he'd come to our next game
你知道博士不能作不了承诺吧？
You know the professor can't make promises, don't you?
我会问他
I'll ask him
只要他记得…
If only he could get to know
我的队友…
each of my teammates...
队服号码怎么样…
What about un form numbers...
我知道了…号码！
I know... numbers!
一切都交给我吧
Leave everything to me
好的！
Sure!
这片叶子也是1
So this leaf is 1, too
对
Right
那是一片叶子
That's one leaf
那棵雪松有那么多叶子…
And that cedar tree with so many leaves
也是一棵树
is one tree, too
一棵树只能算是1，真有趣
It's funny each only counts as one
事实上…
It truly is
定义“1”是很有挑战性的事
Defining "one" is quite a challenge
对你来说也是吗？
Even for you?
很多事我不了解
So many things I don't know
我们来看看
Let me see
好了吗？
Ready?
告诉我…
Tell me,
你现在怎么称呼这个？
what do you call this now?
它像灰尘了，不再是一片叶子
It's like dust, it's not a leaf anymore
没错
That's right
只有完整的时候，它才是一片叶子
It's only a leaf when it's whole
对你来说也是，阿根
It's true of you, Root
和谐的整体是美妙的
The harmony of the whole in an individual is beautiful
这就意味着好
That's what it means to be good
听听
Listen
加时赛取得了胜利…
The walk-off victory The no-hit, no-run game...
七百一十四是…
714 was
贝贝・鲁斯到一九三五年为止本垒打的纪录
Babe Ruth's 1935 career home run record
汉克・阿伦一九七四年八月八日打到道奇队的阿尔・丹宁…
Hank Aaron hit his career total of 715 home runs
投的球，打出了他职业生涯中的第七百一十五个本垒打
on a pitch from the Dodger's Al Downing on April 8th, 1974
进场！
Here goes!
村田作为扎托派克队的投手…
Retired number 11
是穿十一号球衣退役的
is Murayama with the Zatopek pitch
二十三号是吉田
Number 23 is Yoshida
十号是藤村
Number 10 is Fujimura
有天渊，三宅…
There's Tabuchi, Miyake and...
我和教练为你准备的
The r coach and I did it for you
那个根号是谁？
What's the root symbol?
我的儿子
That's my son
你有个儿子？
You have a son?
对！
Yes!
根号会让他和其他队员成为好朋友
A root symbol will share his friendship fairly with any player
我没看见二十八号，那是王牌投手江夏的号码
I don't see #28, ace pitcher Enatsu's number
我们为你留了28这个完全数
We've saved the perfect number, 28, for you
开始！
Play ball!
加油！
Go!
阿根！
Root!
加油！加油！老虎队！
Go! Go! Tigers!
加油，阿根！
Go, go, Root!
按住
Hold this
你好吗？感觉如何？
How are you? How are you feeling?
告诉我你渴不渴
Tell me if you're thirsty
我不该坚持…
I shouldn't have insisted...
都是我的错
It's all my fault
别担心，不严重
Don't worry, it's not serious
你快睡觉吧
You go to bed, now
晚安
Good night
你不该起来的，你还有热度
You shouldn't be up You've still got a f ever
你得休息
You have to rest
脱掉衣服，换套内衣裤吧
Get out of your clothes, let's change your underwear
你昨晚全身被汗水湿透了
You were drenched in sweat last night
我给你换床单，你会觉得舒服点
I'll change the sheets and you'll feel refreshed
为棒球比赛加油一定让你筋疲力竭了
Cheering at the bal game must have exhausted you
对不起，我们坚持要你去
I'm sorry we insisted on inviting you
如果你穿得暖和，吃得好，会康复的
If you keep warm and eat well, you'll recover
阿根也是那样的
Root's that way, too
你该吃点东西了
We've got to get something into your stomach
我拿点苹果汁来好吗？
Shall I bring some apple juice?
我的记忆…
"My memory...
只能维持八十分钟
"lasts only 80 minutes"
我是你的管家
I am your housekeeper
我是受雇来帮你的管家
I'm the housekeeper, hired to help you
我是…
I am...
废人…
Useless...
你帮助我的儿子
You helped my son,
教会我许多宝贵的东西
and taught me something precious
永恒的事实是看不见的…
The eternal truth is invisible...
一定要用心去看
You must see it with your heart
到傍晚，我儿子就回来了
At dusk, my son will join us
我们叫他阿根，因为他是平头
We call him Root, for his flat head
是你取的名字
You named him
你生日是哪天？
What is your birthday?
二月二十号
February 20th
220常常和284有关系
220, eternally bound to
我以为…
I thought...
女人的手是冷的
women's hands were cold
暖和吗？
Are they warm?
这样才暖和
If only this warmth...
对不起
Sorry
情况不妙
This is no good
有人投诉
A complaint
什么？
What kind?
别假装你不知情
Don't pretend you don't know
你犯了大错
You've made a terrible mistake
我听说你在那个数学博士家里留宿了
I hear you stayed over at the math professor's house
我没有犯错
I've made no mistake
你的粗俗暗示冒犯了我
I'm offended by your vulgar insinuation
你知道工作的规矩
You know the rules of your job
是的，很清楚
Yes, very well
未遵守规矩是我不对
I was wrong to ignore them
你坏了规矩，在一个男人的家里待了三个晚上
You break the rules, spend 3 nights in a man's house
这也算是冒犯？
and are offended by insinuations?
但我不能抛下病人
But I couldn't abandon an invalid
我想我只是在履行职责
I be ieved I was only fulfilling my obvious duties
我已经特别优待你的儿子了
I fee I've been especially accommodating about your son
是特殊照顾
It's a special arrangement
我为我的儿子而感激
I'm grateful about my son
对您的照顾感激不尽
I can't thank you enough for your consideration
我的行为不够检点
I was careless in my actions
我道歉
I apologize
我们给你重新安排
So... we'll reassign you
什么？请等一下
What? Please, wait a minute
这是博士的意思吗？
Is that the professor's wish?
是他嫂子的意思
His sister's
我从没有麻烦到他嫂子
I never troubled his sister
我按照她的吩咐自己解决博士的问题
I fo lowed her orders and kept the professor's troubles to myself
她不会管我怎样工作
She's not involved with how I do my job
她怎么能解雇我？
So, how can she fire me?
她知道你留宿了
She knew that you'd been staying over
那她也一定知道他病了
Then surely she knew he was ill
而且他比别的病人更需要照顾
And that he required more care than most invalids
如果我今天不去，博士就会很…
If I don't go today, the professor will be very...
他就要一个人起床…
He's probably getting out of bed,
读他夹克衫上的字条了
reading the note on his jacket all alone...
我想不出有谁能顶替你…
I can't imagine anyone who can replace you...
但我别无选择
But I've no choice
这是最终决定
That's all, it's final
没得商量
No room for discussion
1，2…
1... 2...
4的阶乘是24
The factorial of 4 is 24
真是尊贵的数字
My, what a noble number
行了
Please, come on n
我不时想起博士的话
Now and then, I remember the professor's words
数学规律优美而精确
The laws of mathematics are exquisite, precisely
因为他们在日常生活中是无用的
because they are useless in everyday life
即使找出了所有质数…
Even if the characteristics of prime numbers were determined,
也不能改善生活，没人会因此变得富有
life wouldn't improve and no one would get rich
当然，不管有多背离世界…
Of course, no matter how you turn your back on the world,
很多数学发现都有实际应用
many mathematical discoveries have found practical applications
质数甚至以作密码的形式卷入了战争
Even prime numbers collude in warfare, in the form of secret codes
这是丑恶的一面
It's an ugly fact
但那不是数学的目的
But that is not the purpose of mathematics
数学的唯一目的是探知真理
lts only purpose is to ascertain truth
鼓起勇气睁开你的慧眼
Open your wise eyes with courage
对不起我迟到了
I'm sorry I'm late
欢迎光临
Welcome
咖啡，谢谢
Coffee, please
我们为什么不再去看博士了
Why don't we visit the professor anymore?
事情变了
Things changed
什么事？
What things?
复杂的事
Complicated things
他们说在找人接替你的工作
They say looking after someone, makes them your responsibility
你！
You!
我不担心，因为你那么漂亮
I'm not worried, because you're beautiful
真的？妈妈漂亮吗？
Is that so? Mom's beautiful?
没错，你觉得呢？
That's right, didn't you realize?
因为你漂亮，所以不由担心
That's why it's fine Because you're beautiful
好了
Done
2311，我宣布你是一个质数
Serial number 2311... I pronounce you a prime number
管家，你的电话
Housekeeper, a call for you
来了
Yes
麻烦你真对不起，我知道你很忙
I'm sorry to trouble you, I know you're busy
请坐
Please, sit down
给客人上茶
Some tea for our guest
是
Yes
你究竟在想什么？
What exactly are you thinking?
我儿子做错了什么？
Has my son done something wrong?
问题不在于此
That's not the issue
我把你解雇后……
What do you mean by sending
你还把你儿子送到我小叔子这里…
your son to my brother-in-law's,
你是什么意思？
even after I fired you?
我是什么意思？
What do I mean?
他只有十岁
He's a 10 year old child
他来玩是因为他想来，这还不够吗？
He came to play because he wanted to Isn't that good enough?
对，我知道孩子是无辜的
Yes, I'm sure the child is innocent
我在问你的原因
I'm asking about your reasons
我…
All...
我只想我的儿子幸福
All I want is for my son to be happy
带他和你儿子一起出去，在这里留宿看护他…
Taking him out with your son, staying over to nurse him...
我想不起来吩咐过你那样做
I don't recall telling you to do such things
我承认我超越了职责范围
I acknowledge that I overstepped my duties
但这不是别有用心的
But it was not intentional or calculating
原因很简单
It was simpler
是为了钱？
Is it money?
钱？
Money?
你怎么能这样说？
How... can you say that?
你跟我们别再有任何瓜葛
You're no longer involved with us
我下班时间到了，我回家了
My time's up, I'm going home
因为我们是朋友
It's because we're friends
来和朋友玩也有错吗？
What's wrong with coming to play with a friend?
我的小叔子没有朋友
My brother-in-law has no friends
从来没朋友来看过他
No friend has ever visited him
那我和阿根是他的第一个朋友
Then Root and I are his first friends
我的小叔子每天都会忘记你们
My brother doesn't remember you for even a single day
虽然他这一辈子都会记得我
Although he'll remember me his whole life
对我和阿根来说
For Root and me,
跟博士在一起的时间
the time we spent with the professor
十分珍贵
was really precious
即使只有八十分钟的记忆
Even f his 80 minute memory,
那也没关系
was none at all
直线…
A line...
就像一条直线
Just like a line
一个看不见的永恒的事实
An invisible eternal truth
没错
That's right
如果你用心去看待事情，时光的长短并不重要
If you see things with your heart, time doesn't matter
重要的是现在
What matters is right now
我只想表达阿根的真实想法…
I just wanted to express Root's real feelings...
不
No
你不能折磨孩子
You can't torment a child
孩子要面对…
ChiIdren struggle
比我们大得多的难题
with much larger problems than ours
我也…
I, too...
没什么…
have nothing...
可以失去的了
left to lose
我只能如此
I can only accept what is, as it is
让一切…
Leaving everything
顺其自然吧
up to nature,
过好我生命中的每一刻
living every moment as best I can
…是圆周率
(pi) is the circle ratio, right?
…是-1的平方根，这是个虚数
"I" is the square root of -1 and an imaginary number
这个数字，代表了无穷尽的宇宙
(pi), a number that continues to the ends of the universe,
还有虚数i，从来都不惹人注意
and the imaginary number "i" which never shows itself
最会耍花样的，就是e
What's tricky is "e"
e也叫做纳氏数字，是由英国的
"e" is also called the "Napier number," after John Napier,
数学家约翰・纳皮尔创造的
the British mathematician. The Napier number
纳氏数字是数学里面非常重要的常数
The Napier number is one of the constants, so critical to math
现在，我跟大家探讨结论
For now, I'll just tell you the conclusion
按照运算法则，最后的值为…
If you calculate this "e," its value is...
e = 2.7182818284…！
e = 2.7182818284...
就比如…
This is just like ?
它在不停转啊转
It goes on and on and on forever
这个数字似乎失去了理性
It's an irrational number
像无限的宇宙
From an infinite universe,
圆周率
(pi)...
它来到e的身边
drifts down to "e"
它们握手了
And shakes hands
如果加上害羞的虚数i
with bashful "i"
他们就走在一起了
They come together,
彼此一同呼吸
and hold their breaths
现在，它们之间没有联系
None of them are connected
但如果我们…
But, if a single human
加上一点东西
adds just one thing...
这个世界，就变样了
The world is transformed
矛盾得到了解决
The contradiction is resolved...
答案是，0
Zero,
换句话说
in other words,
它们所代表的，就是虚无的世界
the realm of nothingness embraces them
这个公式，是由瑞士数学家
This formula was conceived by the greatest
十八世纪的里奥纳多・欧拉创造的
18th century mathematician, Leonhard Euler
里奥纳多・欧拉
Leonhard Euler
这就是欧拉的方程式
This is Euler's Equation
他找到了数字之间的联系
He found a natural relationship between apparently unrelated numbers
就比如
This is like...
黑暗中，陨落的星星
A star falling through the darkness
这就是博士的方程式
This was the professor's beloved equation
在夜空中，孤独而美丽的星星
The beauty of a single star in the night sky,
田野中独放的娇艳鲜花
the beauty of a single flower in a field
难以言传
Just as these elude description,
这方程式过于精妙
it's hard to explain the beauty of an equation
我对此还有许多不懂的地方
There's so much I don't know
但博士教导我
But the professor taught me,
要学会去感觉
how important it is to feel
训练自己的直觉
Polish your intuition
培养出数学的敏感
and nurture generous feelings
你们肯定感受到了这美感
I know you can experience this beauty
请热爱数学吧
So please love mathematics
和我一起努力
and work together with me
我妈妈回去为博士工作
My mother went back to work for the professor
你好，我是女管家
Hello, I'm the housekeeper
你穿多少码的鞋子？
What's your shoe size?
二十四码，四的阶乘
24, the factorial of 4
多么尊贵的数字啊
A truly noble number
请进
Please, come on n
这是《数学杂志》的来信，您赢得的大奖
A letter from the Journal of Math You won their competition
这是杂志发行以来最高的现金奖励
It's the highest cash prize since they began publishing
我一直记得
I'll always remember
那天我们初见
The day I first met you
“你闯了进来，打搅了我去爱我的数字”
"You come barging in, interrupting my ove for my numbers!"
“你还责备我了”
You scolded me
我们庆祝吧
Let's celebrate
不需要费事啊
There's no need to celebrate
我们一起庆祝，快乐就会加倍
If we celebrate together, the joy will multiply
我不想庆祝啊
I don't want to celebrate
我所做的只不过偷看了上帝的笔记本
All I did was peep into God's notebook
然后，捏造了一些想法
and copy some deas
不，我们要庆祝
No, we're celebrating
阿根和我都希望这样
Root and I want to celebrate
阿根…
Root...
他是我儿子
My son
你有个儿子？
Oh, you have a son?
是的
Yes
我们一起庆祝阿根的生日
I know, we'll celebrate Root's birthday, too
就在五月十八日
It's May 18th
你来的话，他肯定很高兴的
He'll be thrilled if you're there
他多大了？
How old will he be?
十一岁了
Eleven
十一岁？
11?
是的，要到十一岁了
Yes, he'll be 11
多美妙的质数
A beautiful prime number
特别的，美妙的质数
An especially beautiful prime
就像村田的比赛服上的数字
And it's Murayama's uniform number
太美妙了
That's wonderful
好吧，小孩子最喜欢庆祝活动了
All right, let's celebrate Children need celebrations
五月十八日
May 18th
阿根的生日
Root's birthday
请坐
Please have a seat
阿根，生日快乐
Root, happy birthday
生日快乐
Happy birthday
来吧，阿根
Here, Root
博士，这是给你的礼物
Here's your gift, Professor
给我的？
What? For me?
这是…
This is...
谢谢你
Thank you
深田小姐
Kyoko san
嗯
Yes
我小叔子让我买的棒球手套作生日礼物的
My brother-in-law asked me to buy a baseball glove for his birthday
你也一起来玩吗？
Would you care to join us?
今晚不行
Not this evening
我们出事故之后，我也曾尝试邀请小叔子外出
I had invited my brother-in-law out when we had the accident
但他失去了记忆
and he lost his memory
那场意外，不是我仅仅犯有的错误
And the accident wasn't my only sin
我与父母亲戚朋友都隔绝联系
I cast aside my parents, relatives and friends...
要是我有勇气生下怀里的孩子
If I had had the courage to bear that child...
我们现在的情况…
Our path might have...
我是有罪的女人
I am a sinful woman
现在，一切都要交给你照顾了
I leave everything to you
我会好好对待博士的
I am so grateful to the professor
现在开始…
From now on...
这个家的大门，永远为你敞开
this door will always be open
你拥有一颗敏智的心灵
I can tell you've got a wise heart in there
就像立方根号一样，善于接受一切
Like the root symbol, sharing your friendship fairly
与任何人分享快乐
with anyone
读大学的时候，受伤了
Since that day, until I quit baseball
退出了棒球队
because of an elbow injury in college,
我珍藏着那手套
I cherished that baseball glove
但更可贵的是
But what was far more valuable,
我与教授一起度过的时光弥足珍贵
was the time I spent with the professor, living only in the present
时光的长短，并不重要
Time doesn't matter
我一直在追寻着梦想，与他一起编织的梦想
I'm still pursuing the dreams I dreamed w th him
今天到此为止
That's all for today's lesson
起立
Rise
敬礼
Bow
老师
Teacher
嗯
Yes
谢谢你
Thank you
“一颗沙里看出一个世界”
To see a world in a grain of sand,
“一朵野花里一座天堂”
And a heaven in a wild flower,
“把无限放在你的手掌上”
Hold infinity in the palm of your hand,
“永恒在一刹那里收藏”
And eternity in an hour
“威廉・布莱克”
William Blake
professor TERAO Akira
housekeeper FUKATSU Eri
Root(child) SAITO Ryusei
Root YOSHIOKA Hidetaka
sister-in-law ASAOKA Ruriko
Director/ Screenplay KOIZUMI Takashi
Executive Producer SHllNA Yasushi
Producers ARAKI Miyako SAKURAI Tsutomu
Original Story "Hakase no a shita sushiki" by OGAWA Yoko
Photography UEDA Shoji KITAZAWA Hiroyuki
Lighting YAMAKAWA Hideaki
Recordist BENITANI Kenichi
Art Director SAKAI Tadashi
Music KAKO Takashi
Editor AGA Hideto
Sound Effect SAITO Masatoshi
Decorator SHIBATA Hirohide
Costume Coordinator KUROSAWA Kazuko
Casting SUGINO Tsuyoshi
Assistant Director SAKAI Naoto
Production Manager MATSUMURA Ryuichi
Production Chief NAKAMURA Yasuko
Soundtrack avex-CLASSICS
Piano: KAKO Takashi Soprano: MORI Maki by the courtesy of avex-CLASSICS
"THE PROFESSOR AND HIS BELOVED EQUATION" Film Partners
Asmik Ace Entertainment, Inc., Hakuhodo DY media partners, IMAGICA,
Sumitomo Corporation, Tokyu Recreation Co., Ltd. And SHINCHOSHA Publishing Co.
@2006 "THE PROFESSOR AND HIS BELOVED EQUATION" Film Partners